A Guide to the Francis T.A. Junkin Collection, 1798 - 1918
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Francis T.A. Junkin Collection 1798 - 1918
Thomas Balch Library
M 041
The collection consists primarily of letters to and from Francis T.A. Junkin containing genealogical information, but also a considerable amount of personal family information and letters from other family members. Families included are primarily Junkin, Anderson and Aylett; secondary families include Alexander, Dandridge, Henry, Spotswood, West, Moore, Macon, Reid, and Glasgow.
Teckla H. Cox
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Teckla H. Cox, Leesburg, VA.
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2005.0120, 2008.0003
Biographical Information
Francis Thomas Anderson Junkin was born in 1864 in Rockbridge County, Virginia, son of Anna Aylett Anderson Junkin (1833-1911) and the Rev. William Finney Junkin (1831-1900), a Presbyterian minister. He was the grandson of the Rev. George Junkin (1790-1868), founder and President of Lafayette College in Easton, Pennsylvania, and a President of Washington College (later Washington and Lee University) in Lexington, Virginia. His aunt, Rev. William Finney Junkin's sister, Elinor (1825-1854), was the first wife of Thomas "Stonewall" Jackson (1824-1863).
Junkin attended Kenyon College and Columbia University, where he received a law degree in 1887. He practiced law in New York City until 1898. He was appointed General Attorney of the Atchison, Topeka & Santa Fe Railroad in 1899. He resided in Chicago and New York City, but retained close ties with Lexington and Rockbridge County. His sister, Elinor Jackson Junkin Cox Latane (1867-1939), purchased "Mulberry Hill" in 1903 where she lived with their mother. The property was originally built by Junkin's ancestors and changed hands a number of times in the 19th century. The house still stands on the outskirts of Lexington.
Junkin first showed interest in genealogy in 1878 when he wrote to his mother's cousin, William Winston Fontaine (1834-1917), seeking information about the family. By the early 20th century he was corresponding regularly and at length with relatives regarding family history. He completed a large genealogy chart in 1908, and continued pursuing personal information on the families represented on the chart as well as more distant connections. He married Emily Hutchison Crane (ca. 1866-n.d.) in Paris, France in 1913. On 15 September 1919 Junkin was appointed a member of the Board of Contract Adjustment with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel in the Army. The board was created as a court of final appeals in adjusting claims against the U.S. Government arising after the end of World War I. Junkin lived in Washington, D.C. from 1920 until his death on 6 May 1928.
Francis T.A. Junkin also had connections to the Rust family in Loudoun County, Virginia. His niece, Lily Lawrence Rust Fendall (1880-1973), was the granddaughter of Armistead Thomson Mason Rust (1820-1887) of "Rockland" Leesburg, Virginia and his first wife, Eliza Southgate Lawrence (1828-1958). Junkin's sister, Elinor, was first married to Lewis Berkeley Cox (1856-1901) of "Stoke" in Aldie, Virginia. Their son, William Junkin Cox (1896-1989), was married twice, first to Ida Lee Edwards (1898-1950) and second to Jane Rust (1918-1977). Both women were granddaughters of Armistead Rust and his second wife, Ida Lee (1840-1921). William Junkin Cox's descendants still live in Leesburg.
Scope and Content
The collection includes 9 boxes, with a total of 188 folders covering family information primarily of the Junkin, Anderson and Aylett families. Numerous other relations and connections appear in the collection including Alexander, Dandridge, Henry, Spotswood, West, Moore, Macon, Reid, and Glasgow among others. Oversized materials includes a letter, genealogy research, and six 19th century newspapers. There is also a rolled family chart, with a photocopy for research use.
The collection contains primarily letters to and from Francis T.A. Junkin containing genealogical information, but also a considerable amount of personal family information and letters from other family members, the oldest dated 1798. There are also extracts of wills, deeds and tomb inscriptions dating as far back as 1517. Box 6 contains miscellaneous information unrelated to genealogy but of personal interest to Junkin. It also contains photographs, some made from glass plate negatives, which are stored separately as part of Thomas Balch Library's visual collection (see VC 0038). Box 7 contains eight folders tied together containing copies of original letters found elsewhere in the collection. The numbers in parentheses on some folders refer to Junkin's filing system. They are incomplete and have no meaning in this present compilation.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Ancestry Library Edition, Social Security death index, http://www.ancestrylibrary.com
Foundations of the Past: The WPA Historical Inventory Project in Virginia, Library of Virginia, http://lva1.hosted.exlibrisgroup.com
Francis T.A. Junkin Collection, 1818-1918 (M 041), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA
Leonard, John W., ed. The Book of Chicagoans: A Biographical Dictionary of Leading Living Men of the City of Chicago. Chicago: A.N. Marquis & Co., 1904. http://books.google.com/
Library of Congress Authorities, http://authorities.loc.gov/
Oversized Genealogies and Family Trees: Fleming/Lee/Rust, Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Thomas Balch Library, Loudoun Cemetery Database, http://www.leesburgva.gov/index.aspx?page=940
University of Virginia, "Thomas Jonathan 'Stonewall' Jackson," http://xroads.virginia.edu/~UG97/monument/jacksbio.html
VMI Archives: An Online Historical Research Center, "Stonewall Jackson Timeline and Biographical Summary," http://www.vmi.edu/archives.aspx?id=4933
Washington Post, "Mrs. Emily Crane a Bride: Philanthropist's Widow Marries Sweetheart of 25 Years Ago," 1 May 1913.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
None
Index Terms
Persons:
Anderson, Col. William, 1764-1839; Anderson, Grace Thomas, 1800-1831; Anderson, Margaretta, 1799-1819; Anderson, William A., 1842-1930; Aylett, Martha Dandridge, 1721-1747; Aylett, Patrick Henry, 1878-1943 (great-grandson of Patrick Henry); Aylett, William A., 1833-1900; Cox, Lewis Berkeley, 1856-1901; Cox, William Junkin, 1896-1989; Fendall, Lily Lawrence Rust, 1881-1973; Fishburn, Julia Junkin, 1835-1915; Fontaine, Martha Dandridge, 1795-1875; Fontaine, William Winston, 1834-1917 (great-grandson of Patrick Henry); Glasgow, Catherine "Kitty," 1797- n.d.; Glasgow, Rebekah Anderson, (ca. 1829-n.d.); Jackson, Elinor Junkin, 1825-1854; Jackson, Thomas "Stonewall," 1824-1863; Junkin, Anna Aylett Anderson, 1833-1911; Junkin, Capt. Joseph, 1750-1825; Junkin,Rev. George, 1790-1868; Junkin, Joseph deForest, 1855-1920; Junkin, Joseph III, 1788-1859; Junkin, Joseph, 1750-1825; Junkin, Julia Rush, 1819-1854; Junkin, Sarah Rambo, 1790-1865; Junkin, William Finney, 1831-1900; Latane, Elinor Jackson Junkin Cox, 1867-1939; Miles, Evelyn Trezevant Williams, 1887-1963; Miles, Vincent, husband of Evelyn, 1885 - 1947; Moore, Col. Augustine of Chelsea, 168?-1743; Paxton, Ann Dandridge Junkin Williams, 1860-1945; Preston, Margaret Junkin, 1820-1897; Reid, Lily Thomas, (n.d.); Rust, Armistead Thomson Mason, 1820-1887; Rust, Eliza Southgate Lawrence, 1828-1858; Rust, Ida Lee, 1840-1921
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Society of Colonial Wars, 1907
  - Society of Cincinnati, Virginia Roster, 1908-1909
  - Society of Cincinnati, membership through Aylett, 1895, 1908
  - Proofs of genealogical chart, n.d.
  - Mulberry Hill, remodeling and landscaping, 1911
  - Mulberry Hill, photographs, n.d.
  - Mulberry Hill, purchase, 1903
  - Mulberry Hill, sale, 1914
  - Mulberry Hill, mock-up of sale booklet, 1914
  - Possible house in Chicago, 1910
  - Vincent Morgan Miles & Evelyn Williams Miles correspondence, 1916-1918
  - Vincent Morgan Miles & Evelyn Williams Miles, Arkansas gold mine, 1910
  - Vincent Morgan Miles, 1911
  - Lovick Miles, 1917
  - Evelyn Williams Miles correspondence, 1908-1917
  - George Miles, 1908
  - Junkin, miscellaneous, n.d.
  - Buchanan/Junkin, 1878
  - Junkin, origin of name, n.d.
  - Joseph Junkin descendants, 1878
- (Box 2)
  - Ann Dandridge Junkin Williams Paxton correspondence (folder 1 of 2), 1896-1897, n.d.
  - Ann Dandridge Junkin Williams Paxton correspondence (folder 2 of 2), 1906-1917
  - Joseph deForest Junkin correspondence, 1902-1911
  - Lily Lawrence Rust (Fendall) engagement; Elinor Junkin Cox Latane wedding, 1905
  - Lothrop Withington correspondence re: Junkin, Anderson, Moore, 1911
  - Joseph Junkin II, Revolutionary War, 1896, 1910
  - Rev. George Junkin; Junkin, Galloway, Buchanan, n.d.
  - Rev. George Junkin letter re: death of Thomas "Stonewall" Jackson, 1863
  - Junkin research, 1895-1905
  - Rev. George Junkin, correspondence re: portrait at Washington & Lee, 1909
  - Wallace family, 1907, n.d.
  - Joseph Junkin and Sarah Rambo Junkin, n.d.
  - Estate of Julia Junkin Fishburn (daughter of Rev. George Junkin), 1907, 1915
  - Junkin, research in Ulster, 1907, n.d.
  - James Frederick Junkin, 1906
  - Joseph Junkin III, 1856
  - Rev. William Finney Junkin: speech, 1895
  - Rev. William Finney Junkin, article, n.d.
  - Princeton Theological Seminary with death of Rev. William Finney Junkin, 1901
  - Correspondence re: tombstones for Rev. William Finney Junkin and Anna Aylett Anderson Junkin, 1911-1912
  - Rev. William Finney Junkin, eulogy, 1900
- (Box 3)
  - The Three O'clock Club, 1900
  - Francis T.A. Junkin, letters to Anna Aylett Anderson Junkin, 1906
  - Photograph of portrait by Sully of Anna A.A. Junkin, n.d.
  - Anna A.A. Junkin, letter to Elinor Junkin Cox (Latane) re: "Montrose" at Fincastle, 1900
  - Anna A.A. Junkin, letter to Francis T.A. Junkin re: Aylett, Moore, Alexander, Junkin, n.d.
  - Letter from Rebeka Anderson Glasgow to Anna A. A. Junkin, 1905
  - Letter from William Winston Fontaine describing Anna A.A. Junkin, 1909
  - Anna A.A. Junkin, letter re: her husband Rev. William Finney Junkin, 1908
  - Letter from Anna A.A. Junkin re: Glasgow, Thomas, Reid, Aylett families, n.d.
  - Anna A.A. Junkin, membership in Colonial Dames, 1907
  - Letters from William Alexander Anderson to his sister Anna A. A. Junkin re: Aylett, Spotswood, 1904, 1907
  - Anna A.A. Junkin, letter from her sister Josephine Anderson Poindexter, 1908
  - Anna A.A. Junkin death, 1911
  - William A. Anderson letter to Rev. William Finney Junkin, 1897
  - Alexander, Austin, Arnold, families; booklet, 1896
  - Ellen Bruce wedding, n.d.
  - Virginia Historical Magazine pp. 245-258 "Virginia Troops in Continental Line," n.d.
  - Aylett: letter from William Winston Fontaine, 1908
  - Aylett: portraits, 1908
  - Patrick Henry Aylett, letters, 1907-1908, n.d.
  - Aylett: connection with Lee, 1904
  - Aylett: estates in England, n.d.
  - Aylett: arms, 1908
  - Aylett: research in England, 1645
  - Aylett: possible printing of Aylett letters; also mention of Moore, Todd, West, 1908-1914
  - Aylett letters, question of authenticity, 1908
  - William Winston Fontaine, letter re: Aylett letters, 1908
  - Ann Dansie Dandridge, will, n.d.
  - West and Moore families, 1642
  - William R. Aylett, letter to Francis T.A. Junkin, 1896
  - Ayloffe memoranda, Ann, n.d.
  - John Aylett, land in Louisa County, 1751
  - Aylett, Macon information, 1908
  - William Aylett, York County, 1673-74
  - Letters from William Winston Fontaine re: Moore, Macon, Spotswood, 1908-1913
  - Hening index excerpts from Hening's Statutes at Large: Aylett, Alexander, Moore, Ashton, Crashaw, Anderson, n.d.
  - Ayloffe: 17th and 18th centuries, 1781
  - William Aylett: Clerk of King William County, 1723; member House of Burgesses, 1723-1726
  - Col. William Aylett, 1776
  - Moore genealogy - descendents of Austin Moore, first to come to Virginia, n.d.
  - William Winston Seaton, 1871
  - More (Moore) genealogy: descendents of Austin Moore, first of family to come to Virginia, n.d.
  - Macon, n.d.
  - William Ayloffe of Hornchurch: tomb, 1517
  - Sir William Aylett (Ayloffe): tomb Inscription; became baronet, 1612
  - Aylett, Moore, Todd, Bernard, 1907, 1908
  - Correspondence with Mrs. Charles Fairfax Henley, 1908
  - Aylett: letter from William Winston Fontaine re: copying family portraits, 1911
  - Aylett: William and Benjamin of Braxted Magna, Essex, England; Richard Aylett Northumberland County, Virginia, 1662; also John West 166; Virginia Magazine of History, January 1909
- (Box 4)
  - William W. Fontaine, Francis T.A. Junkin first contact, 1896
  - William W. Fontaine, correspondence to Francis T.A. Junkin re: copying family portraits (folder 1 of 3), 1908-1909
  - William W. Fontaine, correspondence with Francis T.A. Junkin re: copying family portraits; letter re: Francis T.A. Junkin engagement (folder 2 of 3), 1910-1913
  - William W. Fontaine, correspondence with Francis T.A. Junkin re: copying family portraits (folder 3 of 3), 1917
  - William W. Fontaine: to Francis T.A. Junkin; includes copy of copies of Aylett letters in letter of 30 August 1907 - William Aylett to John Aylett, 1907-1911, 1660
  - William W. Fontaine to Francis T.A. Junkin, 1908
  - William W. Fontaine death, 1917
  - West: extract from deed, West to Dandridge, 1719
  - Dandridge, n.d.
  - Thomas, 1896
  - Francis T.A. Junkin correspondence with Lettice Latane re: copying family portraits, 1911
  - Lucy & Maria Harrison of Berkeley, n.d.
  - Katherine Cary pedigree, n.d.
  - Letters from family members acknowledging receipt of Francis T.A. Junkin's genealogical chart (folder 1 of 2), 1908-1915
  - Letters from family members acknowledging receipt of Francis T.A. Junkin's genealogical chart (folder 2 of 2), 1908
- (Box 5)
  - Account of death of Joseph Weir, grandson of Rev. Joseph and Lily Thomas Reid, 1864
  - Letter to Andrew Reid from Rev. William Graham, 1798
  - Letter to Rebecca Anderson Glasgow from Mary Reid, ca. 1860s
  - Thomas and Glasgow correspondence re: copying family portraits, 1896
  - Hugh Thomas: extract from will, 1717
  - Thomas and Glasgow families: connection with Anderson, 1896
  - Anderson/McNutt/Glasgow/Junkin families, 1867
  - Anderson (envelopes), n.d.
  - Photograph of William A. Anderson, Ellen Anderson, and Emily Hutchison Crane Junkin, n.d.
  - Letter from Joseph Anderson to Francis Anderson, Esq., 1833
  - Letter from William A. Anderson re: Graham ancestors, 1897
  - Robert Anderson: emigration from Ireland, 1807
  - Anderson/Glasgow: inscriptions in family Bible; other Anderson information, 1896-1911
  - Letter to Col. William Anderson of Walnut Hill from Samuel Mitchell of Illinois, 1818
  - Letter from Margaretta Anderson to Grace Thomas, 1819
  - Col. William Anderson to Robert and Kitty Glasgow re: death of Francis Thomas (his father-in-law), 1838
  - Francis T.A. Junkin correspondence with William Anderson; letter re: Thomas "Stonewall' Jackson, 1912-1918, 6 June 1915
  - Francis T.A. Junkin letter to Fanny Anderson with personal family news, 1912
  - William A. Anderson: letter re: Thomas, Alexander families; Rebecca Anderson Glasgow interview re: Thomas family, 1895-1896
  - Letter to Anne Anderson from daughters Margaretta (Polly) Anderson and Catherine Glasgow, n.d.
  - Letter from Lily Reid to Rebecca Anderson Glasgow (her niece), 21 April 1861
  - Lily Reid to her sister, Anna Thomas Anderson re: birth of William Anderson Glasgow, 10 February 1825
  - Letters from Lily Reid to Rebecca Anderson Glasgow, 1851-1860
  - Spotswood, Dandridge, Alexander, Anderson, West families, n.d.
  - Information on Campbell, Spotswood, Mosby families, n.d.
  - Glenwood estate sale: correspondence with William A. Anderson re: estate of Francis T. Anderson (folder 1 of 5), 1910
  - Glenwood estate sale: correspondence with William A. Anderson re: estate of Francis T. Anderson (folder 2 of 5), 1910
  - Glenwood estate sale: correspondence with William A. Anderson re: estate of Francis T. Anderson (folder 3 of 5), 1910
  - Glenwood estate sale: correspondence with Williiam A. Anderson re: estate of Francis T. Anderson (folder 4 of 5), 1910
  - Glenwood estate sale: correspondence with William A. Anderson re: estate of Francis T. Anderson (folder 5 of 5), 1910
- (Box 6)
  - Photograph of Francis T.A. Junkin and his wife, Emily Hutchison Crane Junkin, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous, n.d.
  - Sermon, author unknown, n.d.
  - Francis T.A. Junkin appointment as General Attorney for Atchison, Topeka & Santa Fe Railroad, 1899, n.d.
  - Francis T.A. Junkin character from his handwriting, 1905, 1907
  - List of clothing for motor trip, n.d.
  - Lady Godiva pedigree, n.d.
  - Family photographs from glass negatives - most are unidentified, n.d.
  - Photographs from glass negatives (unidentified), n.d.
  - Photographs (unidentified), n.d.
  - New State Mining & Reduction Co.: claim against, 1914
  - Rulers of European countries (in oversize folder 1), n.d.
  - List of kings of England, n.d.
  - Genealogical information not used by Francis T.A. Junkin, 1911
  - Guide to Jamestown 1907 (tricentennial), 1907
  - Information regarding 1st census, 1790
  - History of 1st census (in oversize folder 8), n.d.
  - Dedication of 1st Hudson River tunnel, 1908
  - American Historical Review proposal, 1915
  - American/State Bar Association publications, 1911, 1912, n.d.
  - Kenyon College, 1912
  - Francis T.A. Junkin calling card plate, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous: includes copies of correspondence between John Randolph of Roanoke and Mrs. Gouverneur Morris, 1907, n.d.
  - Correspondence regarding copies of portraits, 1897
  - The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography "Causes of Discontent in Virginia" and "Racing in Colonial Virginia," 1895
  - The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, "Instructions to Governor Berkeley 1642," 1895
  - Brass luggage tag, n.d.
- (Box 7)
  - Moore, Macon, Aylett, Spotswood, Todd, Barnard, n.d.
  - Aylett, n.d.
  - Macon, Moore, n.d.
  - Copy of 1858 letter re: Aylett letters, 1858
  - Macon information and Aylett letters with descriptions of contents, 25 July 1907
  - Aylett letters: queries, n.d.
  - Patrick Henry Aylett, correspondence, n.d.
  - Mulberry Hill, Lexington, VA, n.d.
- (Box 8)
  - List of genealogical articles in Richmond Standard, 1880-1881
  - Lists of genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 19 July 1908-18 September 1910
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 19 July 1908, 25 October 1908-13 September 1909
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 11 October 1908-21 February 1909
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 28 February 1909-11 April 1909
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 18 April 1909-25 July 1909
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 1 August 1909-31 October 1909
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 7 November 1909-16 January 1910
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 23 January 1910-18 March 1910
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 13 March 1910-15 May 1910
  - Genealogical articles in Richmond Times Dispatch, 5 June 1910-18 September 1910
- (Box 9)
  - Genealogical articles from Richmond Times Dispatch. See lists by date and family names at front of box, n.d.
- (OMB 008)
  - European rulers 6th to 17th centuries, n.d.
  - Julia Rush Junkin and Elinor Junkin (Jackson) letter to Margaret Junkin (Preston), 5 July 1844
  - Mrs. Charles Henley Fairfax's information about the Moore family, n.d.
  - William Finney Junkin hospital plan, n.d.
  - Taylor genealogy up to 1859, n.d.
  - Rev. William Finney Junkin genealogy, n.d.
  - Anderson genealogy, n.d.
  - Information on the 1st census, 1790
  - Descendants of Magna Charta Sureties, n.d.
  - Hugh and Elizabeth Thomas descendants, n.d.
  - The New York Herald, 15 April 1865
  - Weekly Rocky Mountain News, 5 October 1864
  - The Rebel, 9 August 1862
  - Soldier's Budget, 24 July 1862
  - Camp Record, 27 June 1861
  - Ulster County Gazette, 4 January 1800
- (VC 0038)
  - Glass plate negatives
- (ROLLED STORAGE)
  - Original genealogical chart of "Alexander, Anderson, Aylett, Bruce, Dandridge, Fontaine, Henry, Junkin, Moore, Poindexter, Spotswood, West, etc."
  - Copy of chart